Register of the Pavel Alekseevich Kusonskiĭ Papers, 1918-1926.
Hoover Institution Archives
Pavel Alekseevich Kusonskiĭ Papers,
1918-1926
29002
Kusonskiĭ, P. A.
12 manuscript boxes (5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, telegrams, orders, circulars, proclamations, lists, maps, and charts, relating to the General Headquarters of the Volunteer Army of the Armed Forces in South Russia; to the Caucasian, Crimean, and other campaigns of the Civil War; to the evacuation and resettlement of General Vrangel''s army; and to Russian emigre military and political life in Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1929.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii.; Refugees.; Russians in foreign countries.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.
Biographical Note
1918-1919 Colonel, White Russian Volunteer Army, Staff of General A. I. Denikin
1919 Officer with the Caucasian Volunteer Army
1921 Major General, White Russian Volunteer Army, and temporary acting Chief of Staff under General Baron Petr N. Wrangel
1922, January Assistant to Chief of Staff in Bulgaria, White Russian Volunteer Army
1922, February Lieutenant General, White Russian Volunteer Army
1923 Deputy of Lieutenant General E. K. Miller, White Russian Volunteer Army
1923-1925 General Officer on staff of General Baron Petr N. Wrangel in Sremski Karlovci, Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes (Yugoslavia)
Series Description
- Numerical Office File of General Headquarters, Volunteer Army, 1918-1926. (Box No. 1-12.)
  Correspondence, orders, circulars, communiques, reports, proclamations, telegrams, and telegram transcripts, lists, accounts, maps, charts, printed materials, protocols, and inquiries, etc., arranged numerically by subject file number.
Container List
- NUMERICAL OFFICE FILE OF GENERAL HEADQUARTERS, VOLUNTEER ARMY, 1918-1926
  - Operative telegrams and reports relating to the First Cavalry Corps of the Caucasian Volunteer Army under General G. Pokrovskii, 1919 and to the Intelligence Service of the Caucasian Volunteer Army, January-May, 1919 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Operative communiques and telegrams relating to the military operations of the Caucasian Volunteer Army, January-April 1919 and to the Don Army, the Headquarters of the North Caucasian Group, the Manych Group, and the Crimean Corps, March-April 1919 (Folder 2)
  - Orders, reports, telegrams, radiograms, maps and lists, relating to the military operations of the Headquarters of the Cavalry Army Corps of the Volunteer Army, November-December 1918, to the First Cavalry Corps, the First Cavalry Division and other troops and formations of the Corps, November-December 1918, to General A. I Denikin's staff, Intelligence Service and troops of the Cavalry Army Corps, December 1918-January 1919, and to the effective composition of the Cavalry Corps, January-March, 1919 (Folder 3)
  - Telegrams, reports and lists relating to the military operations of General Baron P. N. Wrangel's General Headquarters in the Crimea, and to the equipment and battle activity of the Engineering Troops, 1920, and to the Naval General Headquarters, the battle activity of the fleet, equipment and sea transport, April-Ocotber 1920 (Folder 4)
  - Telegrams, letters, orders, reports, proclamations, charts and lists, relating to the formation of mounted troops in General Wrangel's Army in the Crimea, 1920, to the supply question, May-October, 1920, to the Army Air Force, July-October, 1920, and to troop transport and railway activity, May-October 1920 (Box 2., Folder 5)
  - Notes, telegrams, orders, lists, letters, reports and charts, relating to the military operations of the General Headquarters of General Wrangel's army in the Crimea, 1920, and to the effective composition of the Armed Forces in South Russia ("White" armies), March-May, 1920 (Folder 6)
  - Reports, maps, telegrams, notes, charts, lists, instructions, schemes, orders and diagram, relating to the militay operations of General Wrangel's General Headquarters during the Crimean campaign, to fortification of the front positions, May-October (November NS) 1920, to fortification of the Sivash-Perekop positions, March-October, (November NS) 1920, to the fortified area of Kerch and to the defense of Sebastopol, August-October 1920 (Folder 7)
  - Reports, telegrams, orders and circulars, relating to General Denikin's command, February-March 1920, to officers' promotions and seniority September 1919-September 1920, and to the Chief of Staff of General Wrangel's army, May-October 1920 (Folder 8)
  - Day-orders, (No. 2902-3300), ordinances and tables relating to the Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces in South Russia, General Baron P. N. Wrangel, 24 March-June 1920. (Handwritten orders of General Wrangel) (Box 3., Folder 9)
  - Day-orders (No. 3301-3600), ordinances, reports, regulations, lists, and instructions, relating to the Commander-in -Chief of the Armed Forces in South Russia, General Baron P. N. Wrangel, June-Septemer 1920. (Handwritten orders of General Wrangel.) (Folder 10)
  - Day orders (No. 3601-4901), circulars, ordinances, and lists, relating to General Wrangel and to the War Administration of the Armed Forces in South Russia, September-December 1920. (Handwritten orders of General Wrangel.) (Folder 11)
  - By-orders No. 95-188), staff orders (No. 53-140), notifications (No. 294-377) and operative orders, relating to, respectively, the Chief of Staff of General Wrangel, 25 March-27 November 1920; the staff of General Wrangel, 16 March-5 November 1920; the General-on-Duty (Administration Service) of General Wrangel's staff, 6 April-9 November 1920; and General Wrangel April-October 1920 (Folder 12)
  - Orders (Staff orders No. 1-266; Chief of Staff's orders No. 1-22), lists and accounts, relating to General Wrangel's staff, 1921, and to his Chief of Staff, 1921-1922. (Orders signed by Major General P. A. Kusonskiĭ) (Box 4., Folder 13)
  - Orders (Staff orders No. 1-11 and 100-281, by-orders No. 1-2, orders No. 1-2), accounts, lists, inventories, instructions, letter, etc., relating to General Wrangel and his staff, 1922. (Staff orders signed by Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ and E. K. Miller; orders signed by General Wrangel) (Folder 14)
  - Orders (No. 1-106), inventories, accounts and budgets, relating to General Wrangel and his staff, 1923. (Orders to the staff sigbned by Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ, E. K. Miller and F. F. Abramov) (Folder 15)
  - Orders (No. 1-118), relating to General Wrangel's representative in Constantinople, Lieutenant General A. S. Loukomsky, April-December 1920 (Folder 16)
  - Inquests, letters, reports, lists, accounts, protocols, regulations, notes, etc., relating to Lieutenant General P. S. Makhrov, 1921, to the case of Major General Dolgopiatov, commander of the 18th Don Regiment, 1921, and to the Court of Honor of Selimiye Camp at Orhaniye, November 1922-July 1923 (Folder 17)
  - Protocols, letters, notes, acts, reports, accounts, lists, judicial inquests, resolutions, conclusions, etc., relating to irregularities in administration and bookkeeping in the Drozdovskii Infantry Regiment and the Drozdovskii Artillery Division, to illegal actions of officers and men of the Drozdovskii Cavalry Division charged to arrest persons accused of robbery and plunder, 1922, and to the Chief of Workshops of the Engineering Regiment accused of using military materials to execute private orders, 1923 (Box 5., Folder 18)
  - Letters, reports, charts, lists, telegram transcripts, accounts, ordinances, maps, notes, etc., relating to the General Headquarters of General Wrangel's army and to the transportation of army units to Serbia and Bulgaria, their composition, supply and employment, April-August 1921 (Folder 19)
  - Orders, acts, budgets, lists, charts, accounts, notes, reports, ordinances, letters, telegram transcripts, etc., relating to the General Headquarters of General Wrangel's Army and to the transportation of army units to Serbia and Bulgaria, their composition, supply and employment, August 1921-September 1922 (Folder 20)
  - Reports, letters, notes, orders, telegram transcripts, certificates, lists, etc., relating to the General Headquartes of General Wrangel's army and of the transportation of army units to Serbia and Bulgaria, their composition, supply and employment, October 1922- January 1923 (Folder 21)
  - Accounts, reports, lists, charts, rolls, letters, notes, ordinances, circulars, certificates, orders, etc., relating to the General Headquarters of General Wrangel's army and to the transportation of army units to Serbia an Bulgaria, their composition, supply and employment, January-March 1923. (Letters and notes signed by Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ, P. A. Arkhangelskii, E. K. Miller, and others; ordinances signed by General Wrangel) (Box 6., Folder 22)
  - Orders, proclamations, circulars and speeches, relating to General Wrangel and to military, political and socio-economic matters of the Crimean campaign period, 1920, as well as to the Russian Council in Paris, 1921. (Red Army order from 1920) (Folder 23)
  - Reports, letters, charts, notes, telegrams and telegram transcripts, lists, maps, certificates, etc., relating to General Wrangel, his staff, the preparations for the evacuation of the Crimea, the evacuation itself, and the installation of the evacuated army in the zone of Constantinople (repartition by camps, transportation, installation of camps, etc.), March 1920-March 1921 (Folder 24)
  - Reports, estimates, projects, ordinances, letters, accounts, orders, etc., relating to the General Headquarters of General Wrangel, to the Russian General Military Union, June-December 1925, and to conclusions of the Control Commission concerning the rotation of sums advanced from the Militay Fund, 1 September 1922-1 April 1924, and 1 September 1922-1 April 1924, and 1 September 1922-1 October 1924. (Letters signed by General Wrangel), Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ, E. K. Miller, F. F. Abramov, P. A. Arkhangelskii, etc.) (Folder 25)
  - Letters, reports, estimates, accounts, memoranda, notes, ordrs, telegrams, etc., relating to the Headquarters of General Wrangel and the Russian General Military Union, January-august 1925, to the maintenance of the Russian Army in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes and in Bulgaria, 1 April-30 September 1925, and to the Russian Red Cross, June-July 1925. (Letters signed by Lieutenant General E. K. Miller and others) (Box 7., Folder 26)
  - Notes, letters, reports, projects, protocols, extracts, publication, lists, clipping, petition, ordinances, tables, accounts, orders, and by-orders, etc., relating to the Headquarters of General Wrangel, the transportation of army units from Gallipoli and Lemnos to Bulgaria and Serbia, the supplying of these units, and to the Synod of Bishops in the matter of the nomination of clergymen in army and navy units, Mach-august 1923 (Folder 27)
  - Ordinances, protocols, accounts, plans, letters, reports, notes, orders, lists, telegrams, charts, regulations, budgets, credits, estimates, relating to army units and sanitary institutions in Serbia and Bulgaria, and to the transportation of servicemen to other countries, as well as schools and scholarships for their education, August 1923-September 1924 (Folder 28)
  - Map, reports, telegrams transcripts, letters, lists, publication, etc., relatiang to Generals A. I. Denikin and A. S. Loukomsky, General Denikin's officers, and agents, representatives of foreign govennments in South Russia, and military and political questions, including the conflict with Georgia, 1918-June 1919 (Folder 29)
  - Clippings, reports, telegram transcripts, letters, lists, plublication, etc., relating to Generals A. I. Denikin and A. S. Loukomsky, General Denikin's officers and agents, representatives of foreign governments in South Russia, and to military and political questions, including the relations between the govenment of General Denikin and the representatives of the French General Headquarters in South Russia, June 1919-1921. (Handwritten letters of Generals Baron P. N. Wrangel, A. I. Denikin, A. S. Loukomsky and others) (Folder 30)
  - Reports, programs, letters, proclomtion, interrogations, testimonies, notes, tables, orders, telegrams, memorandum, etc., relating to the Information Service of the General Headquarters of General Wrangel and his staff, to the political situation, and to the Makhno movement, 1920-1922. (Bolshevik proclamation) (Box 8., Folder 31)
  - Summaries of telegrams, relating to the Intelligence Service of the Commander-in-Chief, General Wrangel, and to the Situation on the Caucasian, Crimean and South-West fronts, 18 March-27 October (9 November NS) 1920 (Folder 32)
  - Day-book, relating to military operations of the General Headquarters of General Wrangel, 18 April-31 August (13 September NS) 1920 (Folder 33)
  - Communiques and reports, relating to the General Headquarters of General Wrangel and to military intelligence, 5 January-31 July (13 August NS) 1920 (Folder 34)
  - Communiques, reports, charts, maps and lists, relating to the staff of General Wrangel and to military intelligence, 1 August-21 October (4 November NS) 1920 (Folder 35)
  - Telegrams and transcripts of telegrams, orders, instructions, proclamations, reports, notes, maps, etc., relating to the staff of General Wrangel and to military operations and intelligence, 28 May-28 October (10 November NS) 1920. (Orders and instructions signed by General Wrangel) (Box 9., Folder 36)
  - Telegrams, letters, transcripts of telegrams and letters, and official communiques for the press, relating to the General Headquarters of General Wrangel and to the situation on the front, 17 March-28 October (10 November NS) 1920. (Handwritten letter from General Wrangel to A. V. Krivoshein, dated 17 July) (Folder 37)
  - Operative communiques, relating to the General Headquarters of the Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces in South Russia and to the situation on the several fronts, 10 May 1919-28 October (10 November NS) 1920 (Folder 38)
  - Operative communiques and official reports, relating to the General Headquarters of General Denikin and to the situation on the Caucasian and other fronts, 24 April-5 December (18 December NS) 1918 (operative communiques) and 6 December-30 December (12 January 1919 NS) 1918 (official reports) (Folder 39)
  - Letters, circulars, clippings, reports, lists, orders, accounts, testimonies, notes, protocols, etc., relating to the staff of General Wrangel, to the transport of military units to European countries and organization of their work there, 1924-1926, to the political situation in Poland and in Turkey, 1924-1926, to the organizatin of the Russian exposition in Belgrade, 1923-1924, to the inquiry concerning administrative irregularities in the Kornilov Military School, 1922, etc. (Letters signed by General Wrangel, General P. N. Shatilov, Lieutenant Generals E. K. Miller and P. A. Kusonskiĭ, etc.) (Box 10., Folder 40)
  - Reports, letters, lists, proclamations, inventories, agreements, orders, communiques, clippings, charts, telegram transcripts, maps, etc., relating to the staffs of Generals Denikin and Wrangel, to relations with the representatives and military commands of foreign states, involving foreign military aid, and with the Ural Cossacsk, Chechens, and other groups, 1919-1920, and also relating to the Russian military attache in Serbia and to the Hungarian Soviet Amy, etc., 1919. (Handwritten letters and orders by Generals Deniken and Wrangel) (Folder 41)
  - Reports, telegrams and telegram transcripts, notes, declarations, letters, clippings, lists, accounts, orders, programs, chart, etc., relating to the staff of General Wrangel, to Russian military representatives abroad and to political and other questions, 1920. (Letter signed by General Wrangel; letter signed by Lieutenant General E. K. Miller) (Folder 42)
  - Letters, reports, notes, charts, memoranda, telegram transcripts, protocols, estimates, accounts, declarations, etc., relating to the staff and agencies of General Wrangel and to political and financial matters, January-September 1921. (Letters signed by General Wrangel, Lieutenant Generals E. K. Miller and P. A. Kusonskiĭ, Major General S. N. Pototskii, I. P. Aleksinskii, etc.) (Folder 43)
  - Letters, reports, clippings, circulars, projects, ordinances, notes, lists, estimates, summaries, text of address, etc., relating to the staff and agencies of Gneral Wrangel and to political and financial matters, September 1921-August 1922. (Letters signed by General P. N. Wrangel, General P. N. Shatilov, Lieutenant Generals I. A. Holmsen and P. A. Kusonskiĭ, and Colonel A. A. von Lampe, etc.) (Box 11., Folder 44)
  - Letters, extracts, telegram transcripts, declarations, orders, protocols, accounts, notes, clippings, reports, transcripts of press articles, published material, etc., relating to the staff and agencies of General Wrangel and to political and financial matters, August-December 1922. (Letters signed by Lieutenant Generals I. A. Holmsen and P. A. Kusonskiĭ, etc.) (Folder 45)
  - Letters, accounts, reports, notes, published material, extracts, projects, protocols, proclamations, clippings, declarations, etc., relating to the staff, agencies, and military representatives of General Wrangel, to political matters and to questions of general organization, January-August 1923. (Letters signed by General Wrangel, Lieutenant Generals P. N. Kusonskiĭ, I. A. Holmsen, E. K. Miller, and Colonel A. A. von Lampe; copy of an intercepted letter) (Folder 46)
  - Letters, reports, copies of letters and memoranda, projects, protocols, lists, announcements, memoranda, notes, questionnaires, clippings, transcripts of press articles, circulars, estimates, instructions, etc., relating to the staff, agencies and military representatives of General Wrangel, to political matters and to questions of general organization, August-December 1923. (Letters signed by General Baron P. N. and Mrs. Olga Wrangel, Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ and F. F. Abramov, Major General S. N. Pototskii, and Colonel A. A. von Lampe) (Box 12., Folder 47)
  - Letters, orders, ordinances, reports, extracts, notes, protocols, information-sheets, lists, etc., relating to the staff and military representatives of General Wrangel, to political and other matters, 1924, to the Red Army, 1925-1926, and to the Gallipoli Group in Bulgaria, March-July 1925. (Letters signed by General Wrangel, General P. N. Shatilov, Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ, P. S. Makhrov, E. K. Miller, A. S. Loukomsky and F. F. Abramov; two handwritten letters by General Wrangel) (Folder 48)
  - Notes and letters, telegram transcripts, reports, ordinances, bulletins, extracts, copies of certificates, protocols, estimates, circulars, etc., relating to the staff of General Wrangel and to military and political matters, 1923. (Notes and letters signed by General P. N. Shatilov, Lieutenant Generals P. A. Kusonskiĭ, F. F. Abramov, and E. K. Miller, by Colonel A. A. von Lampe, etc.; handwritten letter by Major General I. G. Akulinin) (Folder 49)